# Jen Rogers

jennifer.rogers@tufts.edu https://jenrogers.dev github.com/jrogerthat

RESEARCH FOCUS My research is an articulation between HCl and Visualization. My current work focuses on designing and developing tools to make human-centered processes more transparent and traceable, from human-in-the-loop ML to design studies.

### **EDUCATION** PhD Human Centered Computing

2017-2022 Scientific Computing and Imaging Institute, University of Utah

2015-2016 MSc Medical Visualization and Human Anatomy

Glasgow School of Art & University of Glasgow, With Distinction

2010-2014 **BFA Graphic Design** 

Montana State University, Highest Honors

Skill focus: Visualization. Design and development of web-based tools. SKILLS

> Qualitative research: contextual and semi structured interviews, open-coding Web development: JavaScript, TypeScript, D3.js, React, Flask, Node.js

Programming: Python, (some) Java Design: Adobe Illustrator, Photoshop, Figma

### **PROJECTS**

### Trrracer: Tool for Recording a Design-Oriented Research Process

2021-current

In collaboration with researcher from University of Edinburgh, School of Information Science, to facilitate transparency and traceability

https://github.com/jrogerthat/trrracer

Skills applied: Python (NLTK, Gensim, Flask), TypeScript, React, Electron

### 2022 AutoML Trace: Interactive Sketch

In collaboration with Tableau Research, AutoML Trace is an interactive sketch showing both the context and temporality of human-ML/Al collaboration in data work

Skills applied: requirements gathering, mock-ups (Illustrator), web development (JavaScript, D3.js), Flask

### 2020 - 2021

### Web-based annotation tool for coronavirus cell-entry animations

In collaboration with the Animation Lab. School of Medicine, University of Utah and online community of structural biologists, simulators, and molecular animators.

🥻 https://github.com/visdesignlab/coronavirus\_annotation 🖵 animationlab.utah.edu/cova

Skills applied: requirements gathering, semi-structured interviews, mock-ups (Illustrator), web development (JavaScript, D3.js, HTML5, CSS), Python for image data processing

### Trevo: Visual tool to identify patterns in phylogenetic tree data

Part of the NSF funded Multinet Graph Project, in collaboration with the University of Idaho and Kitware.

🎾 https://vdl.sci.utah.edu/Trevo/ 🖵 https://github.com/visdesignlab/Trevo

Skills applied: requirements gathering, semi-structured and contextual interviews, mock-ups (Illustrator), web development (JavaScript, D3.js, HTML5, CSS), development of interactive audit trail to trace back design study insights to underlying artifacts.

### Composer: Visual cohort comparison tool

In collaboration with the University of Utah Orthopedic Center.

https://github.com/visdesignlab/Composer

Skills applied: requirements gathering, semi-structured interviews, mock-ups (Illustrator), web development (TypeScript, D3.js, HTML5, CSS), Python for data processing

### SELECTED EXPERIENCE

2022 - current

### Postdoctoral Researcher, Visual Analytics Lab, Tufts / Exploratory Science Center, Merck

Research involving high dimensional data visualization and percieved control

### 2017 - 2022 Research Assistant, SCI Institute, University of Utah

Research in web-based visual applications tailored for biological data at the Scientific Computing and Imaging Institute.

### 2021 Intern, Tableau Research

Worked on traceability for autoML. Devoloped taxonomy to characterize artifacts emergent from this process and prototype to visualize the attributes, dependencies, and histories of these captured artifacts.

### SELECTED EXPERIENCE Visiting Researcher, Harmon Lab, University of Idaho

Worked closely with researchers in comparative evolutionary biology to design 2019 and develop a tool for visual analysis of phylogenetic tree data.

### Lab at the Loft, Glasgow School of Art / Digital Health and Care Institute. 2016

Experimental hack-a-thon style design workshop to generate ideas for future projects that improve human interaction with assistive healthcare systems in the home.

### OUTREACH

### Organizing Committee Member NSF Workshop for High-Dimensional Data Visualization,

Organized a 45 participant workshop, from academia, national labs, and industry 2023

### 2021-current

### **Publicity Chair for Biovis**

Assist in outreach for Biovis events at IEEE VIS and ISMB

### 2021-2022

### Publicity Chair for VDS, IEEE VIS 2020

Assist in the outreach for VDS events at IEEE VIS and KDD

## 2020 Publicity and Local Chair BELIV Workshop, IEEE VIS 2020

Assist in the outreach and organization of BELIV workshop at VIS

### TEACHING + MENTORSHIP

### Teaching Mentor, University of Utah.

2018, 2019

Visualization for Data Science (CS 6591). Organized and ran class labs. Designed and built visualization homework projects to teach Javascript and D3.

### 2016-2017

### Ambassador for Urban Uprising Foundation, Glasgow, UK

Mentor and coach for at risk youth from Ayrshire, UK to develop their foundational skills in climbing and progress toward their NIBAS certification. Organized and participated in sea-stack expedition in Northern Scotland to raise money and awareness for the charity.

\* When I am not coding, I am a climbing coach at the local climbing gym

### PEER-REVIEWED Rogers, J., Crisan, A.

### PUBLICATIONS

### Tracing and Visualizing Human-ML/Al Collaborative Processes through Artifacts of Data Work

2023 Honorable Mention at CHI 2023, SIGCHI, ACM

Liu, H., Riggi, M., Rogers, J., Meyer, M., Iwasa, JH, 2022. 2022

A new tool for annotating scientific animations and supporting scientific dialogue PLoS biology 20(8).

Rogers, J., Patton, A. Harmon, L. Lex, A. Meyer, M. 2020

Insights From Experiments With Rigor in an EvoBio Design Study

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (InfoVis)

2019 Rogers, J., Spina, N., Neese, A., Hess, R., Brodke, D. and Lex, A., 2019.

Composer: Visual Cohort Analysis of Patient Outcomes.

Applied clinical informatics, 10(02), pp.278-285.

# SELECTED TALKS +

### Speaker, Invited Highlight Talk

# PRESENTATIONS

BioVis@ISMB 2021

Presented work on tRRRace and traceabiility that came from work "Insights 2021 and Experiments with Rigor in an EvoBio Design Study".

### 2018

### Presenter, Workshop for VAHC 2018, San Francisco, CA, United States

VAHC 2018: Visual Analytics in Healthcare

Presented work on "Composer" interactive cohort analysis tool developed in collaboration with the Orthopaedic Research Center, University of Utah

### 2018 Poster Presenter IEEE VIS 2018, Berlin, Germany

Presented poster for interactive cohort analysis tool developed in collaboration with the Orthopaedic Research Center, University of Utah

### Poster Presenter 2017 SIGGRAPH, Los Angeles, California

Presented poster for "Constellations of Movement", an interactive iPad application visualizing research in motor imagery decoding for the Center for Cognitive Neuroscience, University of Glasgow.

### Poster Presenter and Student Grant Recipient, 2017 IS&T

International Symposium on Electronic Imaging, Burlingame, California Invited to present interactive poster and speak on project developing interactive application to visualize research in motor imagery decoding.

### Invited Speaker Duke of Edinburgh Award Ceremony, Glasgow, UK

Invited to speak to the attending body of the Duke of Edinburgh award ceremony on our climbing expedition to raise money and awareness for Urban Uprising Foundation.